A Guide to the Catoctin Farmers' Club Records, 1868-1983
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Catoctin Farmers' Club Records 1868-1983
Thomas Balch Library
M 034
The collection contains 12 volumes of minutes from 1868 to 1943 (volume 8, 1907-1914, is missing) and unbound minutes from 1944-1983. Minutes are incomplete. Inserted materials include copies of minutes, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous notes and receipts. Following Book 9 is a partial transcription of the volume done by researcher Louisa Hutchison in 2012. The rest of the collection contains correspondence, much of which is between members, to government officials, and to university professors about agricultural sciences. There are also a few essays and speeches, newspaper clippings, magazine articles pertaining to agriculture, grain and cattle price-reports, rainfall and weather tabulations, and other information about the club itself and agriculture in general.
Henry B.R. Brown, Leesburg, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Henry B.R. Brown, Leesburg, VA
Alternative Form Available
Copies of some of the minutes and correspondences are available.
Accruals
1993.0005
Historical Information
One of the many developments in agrarian regions during Reconstruction Era was the rise of farm clubs. Advancements in agriculture stagnated during the Civil War; post war farmers were anxious to resume improvement activities. Continued economic instability after the war prompted farmers to look for new opportunities to stimulate growth. Farmers gained by working together through cooperative purchasing, shared equipment, shared lessons about pesticides and fertilizers, cooperative lobbying efforts in the local government, and the possibility to control farm-hand wages. For a brief time in 1875-1876 local farm clubs in Loudoun County united to form the Grange in Northern VA. The organization did not last long and quickly disassembled into several other farm organizations.
The Catoctin Farmers' Club was established 9 April 1868. Farmers in Waterford, VA held their first meeting at "Clifton," the home of Col. Simon Elliot Chamberlin (1834-1908) to assign committees and draft by-laws. Chamberlin and 13 other men founded the club "to consider the propriety of organizing themselves into a body for the purpose of mutual improvement." They saw economic benefit to pooling their resources. Improving transportation in the area was one of the club's first orders of business. Founders and early members include: Robert R. Walker (1851-1931), J.E. Walker (ca. 1818-n.d.), Elisha H. Walker (1844-n.d.), James Janney (1804-1878), Lewis Steer (n.d.), O.J. Pierpont (ca. 1854-n.d.), Cornelius Shawen (n.d.-1820) - owner of C. Shawen and Co., a general store in Waterford - Isaac C. Hoge (1844-1893), David Mansfield (1802-1871), Samuel Hackney (n.d.), Aaron Hackney (n.d.), Amasa Hough (1831-1905), C.S. Hollingsworth (n.d.), Thomas Phillips (n.d.), R.L.J. White (n.d.), William H. Schooley (n.d.), and Sydnor Bennett (1850-1891).
Throughout the 20th century, the Catoctin Farmers' Club continued to deal with the same agricultural issues which faced farmers at the end of the 19th century. Insects, viruses, disease, and bad weather destroyed the profitability of crop and cattle alike. Veterinary medicines, pesticides, herbicides, fertilizers, and seasonal forecasts were always common discussion points for the club. The club also closely watched for and encouraged technological advancements in farm implements and techniques. They often pooled finances to purchase new plows or other equipment.
Other discussion points and activities were sparked by the local and national landscape. During the home front efforts of WWII the club supported finding domestic sources for materials previously obtained from abroad, like growing rubber in the U.S. The club lobbied Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr. (1887-1966) for assistance when gasoline rationing crippled farmers, keeping them from running equipment. Other issues such as real estate became more complex throughout the 20th century as development rapidly accelerated.
The club's membership in the 20th century reflected some of these issues with which farmers dealt - many of the members as large estate owners were involved in real estate. Bankers, military officers, and prominent businessmen of Loudoun County also filled the club's ranks. Influential members toward the middle of the century included Allen B. McDaniel (1879-1965), Hayden B. Harris (1885-n.d.), J. Churchill Newcomb (1899-1962), and General William C. Crane (1891-1978). The club is still active.
Scope and Content
The collection contains 12 volumes of minutes from 1868 to 1943 (volume 8, 1907-1914, is missing) and unbound minutes from 1944-1983. Minutes are incomplete. Inserted materials include copies of minutes, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous notes and receipts. Following Book 9 is a partial transcription of the volume done by researcher Louisa Hutchison in 2012.
The rest of the collection contains correspondence, much of which is between members, to government officials, and to university professors about agricultural sciences. There are also a few essays and speeches, newspaper clippings, magazine articles pertaining to agriculture, grain and cattle price-reports, rainfall and weather tabulations, and other information about the club itself and agriculture in general.
Arrangement
Box:Folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Ancestry Library Edition, United States census, http://www.ancestrylibrary.com.
Catoctin Farmers' Club Records (M 034), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
FamilySearch.org. Family History and Genealogy, The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, http://www.familysearch.org.
Loudoun Times Mirror (Leesburg), 8 March 1962.
Loudoun Times Mirror (Leesburg), 23 December 1965.
Loudoun Times Mirror (Leesburg), 30 March 1978.
Loudoun Times Mirror (Leesburg), 27 April 1978.
Poland, Charles P. Jr. From Frontier to Suburbia. Missouri: Walsworth Publishing, 1976.
Scheel, Eugene, Loudoun Discovered: Vol. 5, Waterford, The German Settlement and Between the Hills. Leesburg: Friends of the Thomas Balch Library, 2002.
The Washington Post, 2 March 1962.
The Washington Post, 19 December 1965.
The Washington Post, 24 April 1978.
Thomas Balch Library. Town of Leesburg. Biographical Files.
Thomas Balch Library. Town of Leesburg. Loudoun County Cemetery Database, http://www.leesburgva.gov/services/library/cemetery/default.aspx.
Williams, Harrison. Legends of Loudoun. Richmond: Garrett and Massie, 1938.
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
None
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Minutes (Book 1), 1868 - March 1872
  - Reprinted Minutes - Insert, Minutes April 1872 - 1878 (Book 2), inserted at pg. 160, 1877
  - Reprinted Minutes - Insert, Minutes April 1872 - 1878 (Book 2), inserted at pg. 159, 1877
  - Reprinted Minutes and Correspondence - Inserts, Minutes April 1872 - 1878 (Book 2), inserted at pg. 83, 1875, 1882, 1883, 1878, ca. 1875
  - Clipping and Reprinted Minutes - Inserts, Minutes April 1872 - 1878 (Book 2), inserted at pg. 58, 1874
  - Minutes (Book 2), April 1872 - 1878
  - Clipping - Insert, Minutes 1879 - February 1885 (Book 3), inserted at pg. 204, n.d.
  - Correspondence and Clipping - Inserts, Minutes 1879 - February 1885 (Book 3), inserted at front of back, 1879, post 1961
  - Minutes (Book 3), 1879 - February 1885
  - Minutes (Book 4), June 1885 - 1888
  - Minutes (Book 5), 1889 - 1895
- (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Minutes 1896 - January 1899 (Book 6), inserted at pg. 1898
  - Minutes (Book 6), 1896 - January 1899
  - Correspondence - Insert, Minutes 1899 - May 1907 (Book 7), inserted at front of book, ca. 1916, n.d.
  - Minutes (Book 7), 1899 - May 1907
  - Clipping - Insert, Minutes 1914 - 1919 (Book 9), inserted at pg.116, ca. 1916
  - Minutes (Book 9), 1914 - 1919
  - Minutes (Book 9), partial transcription, 1914 - 1919
  - Clippings - Insert, Minutes 1920 - 1928 (Book 10), inserted at back of book, 1926
  - Correspondence - Insert, Minutes 1920 - 1928 (Book 10), inserted at pg. 276, 1928
  - Correspondence - Insert, Minutes 1920 - 1928 (Book 10), inserted at pg. 264, 1928
  - Correspondence - Insert, Minutes 1920 - 1928 (Book 10), inserted at pg. 238, 1927
  - Correspondence and Clipping - Insert, Minutes 1920 - 1928 (Book 10), inserted at pg. 224, 1927
  - Correspondence - Inserts, Minutes 1920 - 1928 (Book 10), inserted at pg. 196, 1926
  - Notes - Inserts, Minutes 1920 - 1928 (Book 10), inserted at pg. 184, 1926
  - Correspondence - Inserts, Minutes 1920 - 1928 (Book 10), inserted at pg. 160, 1926
  - Correspondence - Insert, Minutes 1920 - 1928 (Book 10), inserted at pg. 74, 1924
  - Minutes (Book 10), 1920 - 1928
  - Clipping - Insert, Minutes 1929 - 1937 (Book 11), inserted at back of book, ca. 1930
  - Reprinted Minutes - Inserts, Minutes 1929 - 1937 (Book 11), inserted at pg. 300, 1937
  - Correspondence - Inserts, Minutes 1929 - 1937 (Book 11), inserted at pg. 295, 1937
  - Correspondence - Insert, Minutes 1929 - 1937 (Book 11), inserted at pg. 236, 1934
  - Clipping - Insert, Minutes 1929 - 1937 (Book 11), inserted at pg. 172, ca. 1933
  - Photograph - Insert, Minutes 1929 - 1937 (Book 11), inserted at pg. 156, 1932
- (Box 3)
  - Minutes (Book 11), 1929 - 1937
  - Records - Inserts, Minutes 1938 - 1943 (Book 12), inserted at pg. 117, 1942
  - Notes - Insert, Minutes 1938 - 1943 (Book 12), inserted at pg. 75, 1941
  - Notes - Insert, Minutes 1938 - 1943 (Book 12), inserted at pg. 73, 1940
  - Correspondence - Inserts, Minutes 1938 - 1943 (Book 12), inserted at pg. 71, 1940, ca. 1940
  - Notes - Insert, Minutes 1938 - 1943 (Book 12), inserted at pg. 69, ca. 1940
  - Correspondence - Inserts, Minutes 1938 - 1943 (Book 12), inserted in pg. 24, 1938, ca. 1938
  - Minutes 1938 - 1943 (Book 12), 1938 - 1943
- (Box 4)
  - Extra Copies of Minutes, 1950, 1952, Jan. 1957, June and October 1961, July 1962, December 1972, December 1980
  - Minutes (1 of 2), 1944 - 1948 (January-May and November 1947 missing)
  - Minutes (2 of 2), 1944 - 1948 (January-May and November 1947 missing)
  - Minutes, 1949 - 1953
  - Minutes, 1954 - 1959 (1955, April and June-August and October 1956 missing)
- (Box 5)
  - Minutes (1 of 2), 1965 (Aug. 1961, June and December 1962 missing)
  - Minutes (2 of 2), 1960 - 1965 (Aug. 1961, June and December 1962 missing)
  - Minutes (1 of 2) 1966 - 1971
  - Minutes (2 of 2), 1966 - 1971
  - Minutes, September 1972 - December 1974 (January - August 1972 missing)
  - Minutes, April 1976 - December 1978 (1975, 1977 missing)
  - Minutes, February 1979 - November 1983 (1982 and other misc. missing)
- (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, Clippings, and Data, 1868 - 1899, and undated
  - Correspondence, Clippings, and Data, 1900 - 1930, and undated
  - Correspondence, Clippings, and Data, 1931 - 1936, and undated
  - Correspondence, Clippings, and Data, 1937 - 1940
  - Correspondence, Clippings, and Data, 1941 - March 1943
  - Correspondence, Clippings, and Data, April 1943 - 1951
- (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, Clippings, and Data, 1952 - 1953
  - Correspondence, Clippings, and Data, 1954 - 1965, and undated